Guide to the Henry David Gray Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Writings, Addresses, Sermons, Series VI
  - Related to booklength works
    - Congregational Worshipbook (1978,1984,1990) - correspondence (Box 102, Folder 758)
    - Congregational Worshipbook (1978,1984,1990) - drafts, sources (Box 102, Folder 759)
    - Congregational Worshipbook (1978,1984,1990) - drafts, sources (Box 103, Folder 760)
    - Congregational Worshipbook (1978,1984,1990) - published versions (Box 103, Folder 761)
    - Guide Book to the Holy Land (1965) (Box 80, Folder 587)
    - The Mayflower Pilgrims 1620-1970: Heart of Oak and Helm of Destiny (1970) - notes, drafts, sources (Box 80, Folder 588-590)
    - The Mayflower Pilgrims 1620-1970: Heart of Oak and Helm of Destiny (1970) - published lecture (Box 80, Folder 591)
    - The Mediators (1984) - correspondence with Malcolm Burton, Howard Conn, William Keith, et al (Box 104, Folder 763)
    - The Mediators (1984) - publicity, reviews (Box 104, Folder 764)
    - The Mediators (1984) - draft (Box 81, Folder 592)
    - The Mediators (1984) - published version (Box 81, Folder 593)
    - Pilgrim Fathers Reach the Pacific: A History of the First Protestant Church in Ventura County (1981) - Notes, drafts, sources (Box 82, Folder 594)
    - Pilgrim Fathers Reach the Pacific: A History of the First Protestant Church in Ventura County (1981) - Final version (Box 82, Folder 595)
    - Plus Ultra (autobiography: Vol. I 1983, Vol. II 1985) - Notes, drafts (Box 83, Folder 596)
    - Plus Ultra (autobiography: Vol. I 1983, Vol. II 1985) - Final version, Vol. I (Box 84, Folder 597)
    - Plus Ultra (autobiography: Vol. I 1983, Vol. II 1985) - Final version, Vol. II (Box 85, Folder 598)
    - Plus Ultra (autobiography: Vol. I 1983, Vol. II 1985) - Indexes, Vol. I, Vol. II (Box 85, Folder 599)
    - Science and Religion: A Course for Young People (1948) (Box 85, Folder 600)
    - A Service Book (1966) (Box 104, Folder 762)
    - A Theology for Christian Youth (1941) (Box 104, Folder 600)
    - The Upward Call: A daily devotional study of Philippians for youth (1952) (Box 104, Folder 601)
- Congregational Records, Series VII
  This Series is divided into four sections:
  A. Polity/merger files: chronological sequence of files related to Congregational polity and the merger which resulted in the formation of the United Church of Christ
  B. Congregational organizations: United States (alphabetically)
  C. International Congregational organizations and meetings (alphabetically)
  D. International Congregationalism: correspondence, articles (alphabetically by country)
  - Polity/merger files: chronological sequence of files related to Congregational polity and the merger which resulted in the formation of the United Church of Christ
    - 1910-1913: Commission of Nineteen (Box 86, Folder 602)
    - 1938-1939: "Rethinking Congregationalism" groups (Box 86, Folder 603)
    - 1944-1947: Miscellaneous documents, articles, notes (Box 86, Folder 604)
    - 1948: Including re. Committee of Fifteen on the Union (Box 86, Folder 605)
    - 1948: Letters from the files of Albert W. Palmer (Box 86, Folder 606)
    - 1949: Miscellaneous documents, articles, notes (Box 86, Folder 607)
    - 1949-1951: Proceedings of court case of Cadman Memorial Church of Brooklyn against Helen Kenyon, Moderator of The General Council of the Congregtional Christian Churches of the United States, Volume I (Box 86, Folder 608)
    - 1949-1951: Proceedings of Cadman Memorial Church vs. Kenyon, Volumes II - IV (Box 87, Folder 609)
    - 1949-1951: Proceedings of Cadman Memorial Church vs. Kenyon, Volumes V, VI (Box 88, Folder 610)
    - 1950 Jan-Jun: Miscellaneous notes and articles (Box 88, Folder 611)
    - 1950 Jun-Nov: Including re. formation Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 88, Folder 612)
    - 1950 Dec: Including re. first meeting of Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 88, Folder 613)
    - 1951 Jan-Feb: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity and its Subcommittee on the Congregational Polity (Box 89, Folder 614)
    - 1951 Mar: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 615)
    - 1951 Apr: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 616)
    - 1951 May-Jul: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 617)
    - 1951 Aug-Nov: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 618)
    - 1951: Whittaker questionnaire on Congregational Christian polity (Box 89, Folder 619)
    - 1952 Jan-Apr: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 620)
    - 1952 May-Dec: incl. report "Congregational Polity as Described in its Constitutional Documents" (Box 89, Folder 621)
    - 1952, n.m.: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 89, Folder 622)
    - 1952-1953: Replies to HDG inquiry re. Congregational Polity: A - H (Box 89, Folder 623)
    - 1952-1953: Replies to HDG inquiry re. Congregational Polity: J - W (Box 90, Folder 624)
    - 1952-1953: Regional panels and Educators' panel of Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 90, Folder 625)
    - 1953 Jan-Jun: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity, including statement by Roland Bainton (Box 90, Folder 626)
    - 1953 Jun: Version of "Congregational Polity as it is Practiced in the United States" (Box 90, Folder 627)
    - 1953 Jul-Dec: Including re. Cadman Memorial Church of Brooklyn court case (Box 90, Folder 628)
    - 1953 Dec: Version of "Congregational Polity as it is Practiced in the United States" (Box 90, Folder 629)
    - 1953-1954: Responses to "Congregational Polity as it is Practiced in the United States": A - H (Box 90, Folder 630)
    - 1953-1954: Responses to "Congregational Polity as it is Practiced in the United States": J - W (Box 91, Folder 631)
    - 1954 Jan: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 91, Folder 632)
    - 1954 Feb: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 91, Folder 633)
    - 1954 Feb: Version of "Congregational Polity as it is Practiced in the United States" (Box 91, Folder 634)
    - 1954 Mar-May: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 91, Folder 635)
    - 1954 Jun: The Report of a Study by the Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity (Box 91, Folder 636)
    - 1954 Jun-Sep: Committee on Free Church Polity and Unity; General Council Meeting in New Haven (Box 92, Folder 637)
    - 1954 Oct-Dec: Merger issues/ incl. re. Joint Meeting, Cleveland and "Claremont Resolution" (Box 92, Folder 638)
    - 1955 Jan-Jun: Merger issues/ incl. re. Commission on the Study of the Constitutional Problem (Box 92, Folder 639)
    - 1955 Jul-Oct: Merger issues/ incl. re. Committee for the Continuation of the Congregational Christian Churches of the U.S. (Box 92, Folder 640)
    - 1955 Nov-Dec, n.m.: Merger issues/ incl. re. Commission on the Study of the Constitutional Problem (Box 92, Folder 641)
    - 1956 Jan-Feb: Merger issues/ incl. formation of National Association of Congregational Christian Churches (Box 92, Folder 642)
    - 1956 Mar: Merger issues (Box 92, Folder 643)
    - 1956 Apr: Merger issues (Box 92, Folder 644)
    - 1956 May: Merger issues/ incl. re. League to Uphold Congregational Principles (Box 92, Folder 645)
    - 1956 Jun: Merger issues/ Cleveland meeting/ General Council meeting Omaha (Box 92, Folder 646)
    - 1956 Jul-Dec: Merger issues (Box 92, Folder 647)
    - 1957 Jan-May: Merger issues (Box 93, Folder 648)
    - 1957 Jun-Dec: Merger issues/ incl. re. Uniting General Synod for the United Church of Christ (Box 93, Folder 649)
    - 1958 Jan-May: Merger issues (Box 93, Folder 650)
    - 1958 Jun-Dec: Merger issues (Box 93, Folder 651)
    - 1959 Mar-Jun: Merger issues (Box 93, Folder 652)
    - 1959 Jul: Merger issues/ Report of the Commission to Prepare a Constitution for the United Church of Christ (Box 93, Folder 653)
    - 1959 Aug-Dec: Merger issues (Box 93, Folder 654)
    - 1960 Jan-Aug: Merger issues/ incl. re. constitution of the UCC (Box 93, Folder 655)
    - 1960 Sep-Oct: Merger issues/ incl. re. constitution of the UCC (Box 94, Folder 656)
    - 1960 Nov-Dec: Merger issues/ incl. re. formation of Fellowship of Connecticut Congregational Churches (Box 94, Folder 657)
    - 1961 Jan: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 658)
    - 1961 Feb-Mar: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 659)
    - 1961 Apr-Jul: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 660)
    - 1961 Aug-Dec: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 661)
    - 1961: First Congregational Church, Burlington, Iowa court case (Box 94, Folder 662)
    - 1962: Merger issues/ incl. re. court case involving Saginaw, Michigan church (Box 94, Folder 663)
    - 1963: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 664)
    - 1964-1965: Merger issues (Box 94, Folder 665)
    - 1966-1967: Merger issues/ incl. re. Mayflower Church court case (Box 95, Folder 666)
    - 1970-1978: Merger issues (Box 95, Folder 667)
    - 1979-1980: Merger issues/ incl. re. Groton, Connecticut church court case (Box 95, Folder 668)
    - Undated documents: writings and notes of HDG (Box 95, Folder 669)
    - Undated documents: re. constitution of UCC (Box 95, Folder 670)
    - Undated documents: miscellaneous, typescript format (Box 95, Folder 671)
    - Undated documents: miscellaneous, printed format (Box 95, Folder 672)
    - Undated documents: I.M. Pious letters (Box 95, Folder 673)
  - Congregational organizations: United States
    - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (Box 96, Folder 674)
    - American Congregational Association (Box 96, Folder 675)
    - American Congregational Center (see Series I)
    - Association of Congregational Christian Churches and Ministers of California and Neighboring Western States, Inc. (Box 96, Folder 677-680)
    - Board of Home Missions of the Congregational Christian Churches (Box 96, Folder 681)
    - California Association of Congregational Christian Churches and Ministers (Box 96, Folder 682)
    - Committee for the Continuation of Congregational Churches (Box 96, Folder 683)
    - Congregational Christian Churches - Missions Council (Box 96, Folder 684)
    - Congregational Christian Churches - Midwinter meetings, 1952 (Box 96, Folder 685)
    - Congregational Education Society (Box 97, Folder 686)
    - Connecticut Fellowship of Congregational Christian Churches (Box 97, Folder 687-691)
    - Conservative Congregational Christian Conference (Box 97, Folder 692)
    - Consultation of the Nature and Future of the Free Church (Box 97, Folder 693)
    - Council of Community Churches (Box 97, Folder 694)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Grand Rapids meeting, 1944 (Box 97, Folder 695)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Grinnell meeting, 1946 (Box 97, Folder 696)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Cleveland meeting, 1950 (Box 97, Folder 697)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Claremont meeting, 1952 (Box 98, Folder 698)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Committee on Denominational History (Box 98, Folder 699)
    - General Council of Congregational Christian Churches - Theological Commission (Box 98, Folder 700)
    - Hollywood Congregational Center for Study and Service (see Series I)
    - Laymen's Study Group, Inc. (Box 98, Folder 702)
    - League to Uphold Congregational Principles (Box 98, Folder 703)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Minutes, documents, correspondence: 1955-1960 (Box 98, Folder 704)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 98, Folder 705)
    - 1963 (Box 98, Folder 706)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 98, Folder 707)
    - 1966 (Box 98, Folder 708)
    - 1967 (Box 98, Folder 709)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 98, Folder 710)
    - 1970 (Box 98, Folder 711)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 98, Folder 712)
    - 1973,n.d. (Box 99, Folder 713)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Addresses (Box 99, Folder 714)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Commission on Christian Education/ Commission on Youth (Box 99, Folder 715)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Commission on Publications (Box 99, Folder 716)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Congregational Foundation for Theological Studies (Box 99, Folder 717)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Corrrespondence course for lay preachers (Box 99, Folder 718)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Handbook, 1962 (Box 99, Folder 719)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: Missionary Society/ Commission on Missions (Box 99, Folder 720)
    - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches: World Christian Relations Commission (Box 99, Folder 721)
    - Pennsylvania Association of Congregational Churches (Box 99, Folder 723)
  - International Congregational organizations and meetings:
    - Congregational World Assembly of Youth (C-WAY) 1985 - Preparations (Box 99, Folder 724)
    - Congregational World Assembly of Youth (C-WAY) 1985 - Delegates: recruitment, correspondence (Box 99, Folder 725-726)
    - Congregational World Assembly of Youth (C-WAY) 1985 - Delegates: information letters (Box 100, Folder 727)
    - Congregational World Assembly of Youth (C-WAY) 1985 - Program (Box 100, Folder 728)
    - Congregational World Assembly of Youth (C-WAY) 1985 - Post-meeting plans for delegates (Box 100, Folder 729)
    - International Congregational Council Wellesley 1949 (Box 100, Folder 730)
    - International Congregational Council, St. Andrews, 1953 (Box 100, Folder 731)
    - International Congregational Council, Hartford, 1958 (Box 100, Folder 732)
    - International Congregational Fellowship (Box 100, Folder 733-734)
  - International Congregationalism: correspondence, articles
    - General (Box 100, Folder 735)
    - Argentina (Box 100, Folder 736)
    - Australia and New Zealand (Box 100, Folder 737)
    - Brazil (Box 100, Folder 738)
    - Britain (Box 100, Folder 739)
    - General - Congregational Federation (Box 100, Folder 740)
    - General - Congregational History Circle (Box 100, Folder 741)
    - General - Pilgrim Fathers' Memorial Church (Box 101, Folder 742)
    - Germany (Box 101, Folder 743-744)
    - Greece (Box 101, Folder 745)
    - Honduras (Box 101, Folder 746)
    - Hong Kong (Box 101, Folder 747)
    - India (Box 101, Folder 748)
    - Italy (Box 101, Folder 749)
    - Mexico (Box 101, Folder 750)
    - Middle East (Box 101, Folder 751)
    - Nigeria (Box 101, Folder 752-753)
    - Samoa (Box 101, Folder 754)
    - South Africa (Box 101, Folder 755)
    - Taiwan (Box 101, Folder 756)